A Guide to the Virginia Wilderness Committee Collection, 1969-2009
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Virginia Wilderness Committee Collection1969-2009
Special Collections, James Madison University
5032
5 boxes (2.09 linear feet), plus 56 oversize maps stored within four folders in the map case in Special Collections
The Virginia Wilderness Committee Collection, 1969-2009, is comprised of 2.09 linear feet of documents pertaining to the organization's people, finances, meetings, newsletters, and projects, which include wilderness legislation, preservation, and protection in Virginia's National Forests and other wild areas.
J. James and Elizabeth Murray/ Virginia Wilderness Committee
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
J. James and Elizabeth Murray donated this collection in March of 2010.
Provenance
The donor reserves copyright of the following two items until March 1, 2020: Virginia Wilderness Committee: Forty Years; Recollections in 2009 by Jim Murray; and Virginia Wilderness Bill 2000.
Biographical Information
The Virginia Wilderness Committee (VWC) consists of a group of citizens whose goal is to preserve and protect wild areas in Virginia. It was established in May of 1969 during a workshop meeting organized by The Wilderness Society. The first leadership council consisted of John McKnight of Williamsburg as the first chairman, J. James "Jim " Murray, the donor of this collection, as vice-chairman, and Lloyd Sumner as secretary treasurer. The VWC and The Wilderness Society immediately joined forces to found the Virginia Conservation Council in order to serve as an umbrella organization for Virginia's growing number of wilderness-oriented organizations. In 1976, the VWC played a role in adding additional acreage to the Shenandoah National Park wilderness proposal. The VWC also campaigned for the Virginia Wilderness Act of 1984, a major piece of legislation that designated 10 areas for wilderness protection. In the 1990s, some members of Congress opposed additional wilderness designation legislation. During this time, the VWC focused on protecting wild areas, opposing the construction of a gas pipeline through potential future wilderness designated areas, compiling and publishing a memorial book on Ernie Dickerman, an important member of the VWC who passed in 1998, and other projects. In the early 2000s, the VWC was involved in the revision of the management plan for the Thomas Jefferson National Forest, as well as with the Virginia Wilderness Act of 2000. In 2009, the Virginia Ridge and Valley Act was finally passed within an omnibus bill. The VWC had tracked and campaigned for this bill since it was first introduced in 2004. The 2009 Act designated 53,000 acres of land in Virginia as wilderness.
VWC's major concern has been working with in order to pass legislation to designate specific wild areas as "wilderness." With this designation, an area is entitled to a certain level of protection under the Wilderness Act of 1964. The VWC has also been concerned with beach traffic, air quality, water quality, dams, wildlife and endangered species, power lines, wilderness usage, roads, Virginia's National Forests, the National Park Service, oil drilling in the arctic, wilderness trails, eminent domain, etc.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Wilderness Committee Collection, 1969-2009, is comprised of 2.09 linear feet of documents pertaining to the organization's people, finances, meetings, newsletters, and projects, which includes wilderness legislation, preservation, and protection in Virginia's National Forests and other wild areas. The collection contains 56 oversize maps, which are stored in the map case in Special Collections. The collection consists of 14 series, described at folder level.
Series One, VWC Administrative Items, 1969-2009 consists of documents such as the organization's by-laws, membership lists, meeting agendas and minutes, and brochures.
Series Two, VWC Financial Documents, 1981-2008 contains account ledgers, financial reports, grants, tax information, and other items pertinent to the organization's finances.
Series Three, VWC Newsletters, 1970-2009 includes three folders of the organization's newsletter mailings.
Series Four, Legislation, 1962-2009 [bulk 1962-1985, 2000-2009] consists of mailing lists, Congressional speeches, correspondence, public notices, and documents used by the members of VWC as evidence for building a case in favor of wilderness designation or wild area protective legislation in Virginia.
Series Five, VWC Files on People and Personnel, 1961-2008 [bulk 1998] is composed of documents compiled by the donors on a variety of people important to the organization, including members of Congress, VWC personnel, and important people from other organizations.
Series Six, VWC Files on Related Organizations, 1968-2009 includes documents compiled by the donors on a variety of related organizations and committees that the VWC interacted with.
Series Seven, General Forest Planning and Management Documents, 1970-2001 is comprised of planning reports and agenda relating to managing and creating wilderness areas.
Series Eight, George Washington National Forest, 1969-2009 includes documents related to the VWC's involvement in Washington National Forest's management revisions and plans, as well as many folders compiled by the organization pertaining to key areas within Washington National Forest. Some area folders consist of information about their potential for wilderness designation, special management for the area, campaigns to protect and preserve areas, basic information, maps, and relevant news clippings.
Series Nine, Thomas Jefferson National Forest, 1971-2009 includes documents related to the VWC's involvement in Jefferson National Forest's management revisions and plans, as well as many folders compiled by the organization pertaining to key areas within Jefferson National Forest. Some area folders consist of information about their potential for wilderness designation, special management for the area, campaigns to protect and preserve areas, basic information, maps, and relevant news clippings.
Series Ten, VWC Projects/Interests/Activities, 1970-2007 contains items pertaining to the various projects, interests, and activities of the Virginia Wilderness Committee. These documents relate to general environmental concerns and feature issues that while not directly related to the Virginia Wilderness Committee or Wilderness, are still relevant to the VWC as a whole.
Series Eleven, VWC Miscellaneous is one folder which contains items that did not fit in other series of the collection.
Series Twelve, VWC Photo Series contains 2000 Wilderness Bill photos and miscellaneous photos featuring wilderness areas. The 2000 Wilderness Bill photos feature a celebratory hike and party after the bill was made into law. Various wilderness areas include: Shenandoah National Park, Cave Springs/Stone Mountain, Brush Mountain East, Brush Mountain (Montgomery County), Brushy Mountain (Bland County), Hunting Camp Creek, Long Spur, Little Walker Mountain, and Lynn Camp Creek. Negatives are also included of the Little River area, Long Spur, and Shenandoah National Park.
Series Thirteen, Jumpdrive contains a USB drive which includes further information about the VWC. Some items were printed from the drive, and a sheet of paper is included in the folder to indicate which items from the drive were printed. About 25% of the items on the drive were printed. These documents include correspondence, fact sheets, meeting minutes for other organizations such as Friends of Shenandoah, and financial and administrative documents.
Series Fourteen, Oversize Maps contain maps from the Campaign for the Virginia Wilderness Act of 2010. There are four map sets total. These sets are stored in the map case in Special Collections, separated into folders by set. These sets include: map set of the original proposal, 2002; working map set of 2003; forest service working map set of January 2004; forest service working map set of July 2004. These are digitally created maps which feature different areas of wilderness.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 14 series:
I: VWC Administrative Items
II: VWC Financial Documents
III: VWC Newsletters
IV: Legislation
V: Files on People/Personnel
VI: Files on Related Organizations
VII: General Area Planning and Management Documents
VIII: Geroge Washington National Forest
IX: Thomas Jefferson National Forest
X: VWC Projects/Interests/Activities
XI: Miscellaneous
XII: Photos
XIII: Jumpdrive
XIV: Oversize Maps
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Murray, Jim. "Virginia Wilderness Committee: Forty Years. Recollections in 2009, " 2009. Virginia Wilderness Committee http://www.vawilderness.org/about
Related Material
Ernest M. Dickerman Papers, SC#3085
The U.S. Forest Service, George Washington National Forest, Dry River District Collection, SC# 3014
The U.S. Forest Service, George Washington National Forest, Lost River and Massanutten Working Circles Collection, SC# 2086
Contents List
- VWC Administrative Items
  - Early Documents, 1969 (Box-folder 1:1)
    ‐ Membership roster and addresses, newspaper clippings, report from Virginia Wilderness Conservation Workshop.
  - By-laws (Box-folder 1:2)
    ‐ committee bylaws with written corrections as well as a finished copy.
  - Membership lists, 1981-1985, 1990-1994 and undated (Box-folder 1:3)
    ‐ membership lists with addresses.
  - Annual General Meeting Documents, 1971, 1994, 1997-2007, 2009 (Box-folder 1:4)
    ‐ minutes, agendas, and officer reports.
  - Buffalo Gap Meetings, 1999-2004 and undated (Box-folder 1:5)
    ‐ agenda and notes from meetings.
  - Brochures (Box-folder 1:6)
    ‐ letter to officers and VWC brochures.
  - Early Correspondence, 1968-1990 (Box-folder 1:7)
    ‐ letters and reports from the organization’s early years (70s to late 80s).
  - Record Statements, 1970-1999 (Box-folder 1:8)
    ‐ letters and press releases which provide statements regarding the VWC’s position on legislation and events.
  - Further Correspondence and Statements, 1990-1999 (Box-folder 1:9)
    ‐ letters and clippings from the 1990s.
  - VWC Press Clippings, 1981-1999 (Box-folder 1:10)
    ‐ newspaper clippings relating to environmental interests of the VWC.
  - VWC Press Clippings, 2000-2008 (Box-folder 1:11)
- VWC Financial Documents
  - Account Ledgers, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 1:12)
    ‐ Planters Bank and Trust savings passbook and deposit account, Income and Expenses Book beginning June 1, 1981.
  - Financial Reports and Treasury Documents, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 1:13)
    ‐ handwritten and typed reports and letters from various VWC treasurers: Jo Anne Pierce, David Browning, and Juliana Simpson.
  - Royalty Income Documents, 1985-1998 (Box-folder 1:14)
    ‐ statements and check/voucher invoices from The East Wood Press and The Globe Pequot Press for book royalties (Hiking Virginia’s National Forests).
  - Wyss Family Foundation Grants, 1998-2008 (Box-folder 1:15)
    ‐ correspondence relating to the grant and how grant money was used, as well as annual updates to the foundation of the VWC’s progress, VWC July 2007, December 2008 newsletters, one page about "Friends of Shenandoah Mountain."
  - Patagonia Grant, 2002 (Box-folder 1:16)
    ‐ correspondence and other documents relating to the grant.
  - Tax Documents, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 1:17)
    ‐ correspondence relating to tax returns and Employee Identification Numbers.
- VWC Newsletters
  - Virginia Wilderness Committee Newsletters I, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Virginia Wilderness Committee Newsletters II, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Virginia Wilderness Committee Newsletters III, 1990-20099 (Box-folder 1:20)
- Legislation
  - National Forest Wild Areas Legislation, 1962-1972 and undated (Box-folder 1:21)
    ‐ correspondence, statements, and other documents relating to understanding The Wilderness Act and criteria for identification; "Wilderness Report" from The Wilderness Society; copies of proposed Senate Bills, "National Forest Wild Areas Act of 1972" and "National Forest Wild Areas Act of 1973."
  - Wetlands Legislation, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Omnibus Wilderness Bill, 1972- 1975 and undated (Box-folder 1:23)
    ‐ statements; congressional records; "Wilderness Report" from The Wilderness Society; correspondence; report from the Virginia Wilderness Committee which contains input in the Eastern Wilderness Hearings. Memoranda from "Citizens for Eastern Wilderness."
  - National Forest Timber Management Reform Act of 1976 (Box-folder 1:24)
    ‐ Congressional Record, Action Alert calling for support of act, Sierra Club correspondence.
  - Virginia Wilderness Bill, 1984: 1980-1984 (Box-folder 1:25)
    ‐ correspondence and statements; proposed areas list; Shenandoah Valley Wilderness Conference Agenda, 1983; newspaper clippings; sample letters to congressional representatives.
  - Virginia Wilderness Act of 2000 Part 1 July 1993-August 2000 (Box-folder 1:26)
    ‐ dated materials relating to support of the Act, such as correspondence, newspaper clippings.
  - Virginia Wilderness Act of 2000 Part 2, September 2000- June 2001 (Box-folder 1:27)
    ‐ materials relating to the passage of the act, such as newspaper clippings and correspondence.
  - Virginia Wilderness Act, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 1:28)
    ‐ memoranda, correspondence, agenda, strategy issues, areas endorsed for national scenic area status, draft of the act, Wilderness Progress Update, information about possible wilderness areas.
  - Virginia Ridge and Valley Act/Omnibus Bill Part 1, 2004-2006 (Box-folder 1:29)
    ‐ dated materials relating to the Act, such as: endorsements, email and letter correspondence; copies and drafts of proposed bill; maps of proposed Wilderness Areas.
  - Virginia Ridge and Valley Act/Omnibus Bill Part 2, 2007-2009 (Box-folder 1:30)
    ‐ dated materials relating to the Act, such as: modifications to the act; correspondence and memoranda; testimonies before the Senate and House of Representatives; newspaper clippings.
  - Wilderness Bill Proposals, 1991-1999 (Box-folder 1:31)
    ‐ publicity relating to the bill.
  - Wilderness Bill Publicity, 2009 (Box-folder 1:32)
    ‐ correspondence, memoranda, program notes of Conservation Council of Virginia relating to proposed Coastal Wetlands Act for Virginia as well as notes from the Wetlands Study Commission, copies of relevant newspaper clippings, and a copy of Wetlands Bill.
- Files on People/Personnel
  - George Allen, 1991-2004, and undated (Box-folder 1:33)
    ‐ correspondence to and from Senator George Allen.
  - Rick Boucher, 1998-2002 (Box-folder 1:34)
    ‐ correspondence to and from Senator Rick Boucher.
  - Bill Damon, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 1:35)
    ‐ Forest Supervisor’s report; correspondence to and from.
  - Ernie Dickerman, 1961-1998, Part One: Memoranda, 1976-1991 (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Ernie Dickerman, 1961-1998, Part Two: Misc. Documents, 1984-1998 (Box-folder 1:37)
  - Ernie Dickerman, 1961-1998, Part Three: Christmas Letters, 1961-1997 (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Ernie Dickerman, 1961-1998, Part Four: "Ernie Dickerman: A Tribute," 1999 (Box-folder 1:39)
    ‐ The Wilderness Society tribute to Ernie Dickerman, photocopied pictures of Ernie.
  - Vernon Garber (Box-folder 1:40)
    ‐ "A Remembrance" written by Lynn Cameron.
  - Donald Giecek, 2001-2006, and undated (Box-folder 1:41)
    ‐ letters from; resume; contract between Giecek and the Virginia Wilderness Committee; progress reports.
  - Elizabeth Murray, 1981-2008, and undated (Box-folder 1:42)
    ‐ handwritten notes and letters from Elizabeth; "Virginia Wilderness ---with a capital W" submission to Country Magazine; notes for various presentations to clubs and panels; "Wilderness Advocacy in Virginia", March 2005 for Southern Environmental Law Center writing contest.
  - Mark Miller, 2002-2003, and undated (Box-folder 1:43)
    ‐ correspondence from, handwritten notes, goals for Wilderness campaign.
  - John Warner, 1997-2001 (Box-folder 1:44)
    ‐ correspondence to and from Senator John Warner; information on suggested Wilderness areas; memorandum to John Warner.
  - David A. West, 2005 (Box-folder 1:45)
- Files on Realted Organizations
  - Appalachian Forest Management Group, 1988-1989, and undated (Box-folder 2:1)
    ‐ newsletters; relevant newspaper articles and editorials.
  - Appalachian Trail Club, 1970-2005 (Box-folder 2:2)
    ‐ "For immediate release" statements; scans of newspaper articles; trail notes and comments; draft policy statement on Wilderness.
  - American Wilderness Coalition, 2002-2003, and undated (Box-folder 2:3)
    ‐ rapid response grants program; letter from Coalition to Jim Murray.
  - Citizens for Albemarle, 1975, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 2:4)
    ‐ correspondence, agenda, reports, minutes.
  - Conservation Council of Virginia Part I, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 2:5)
    ‐ dated materials containing statements; correspondence; reports; by-laws.
  - Conservation Council of Virginia Part II, 1974-1987, and undated (Box-folder 2:6)
    ‐ dated materials containing correspondence; statements; reports; minutes.
  - Greater Newport Rural Historic District Committee, 1997 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Rockbridge Conservation Council and Valley Conservation Council (Box-folder 2:8)
    ‐ brochure and membership application.
  - Sierra Club (Piedmont and Old Dominion Chapters), 1975-1984, and undated (Box-folder 2:9)
    ‐ correspondence; "Trailblazes" and "Old Dominion Sierran" newsletters.
  - Shenandoah Ecosystems Defense Group, 1997 (Box-folder 2:10)
    ‐ one newsletter, "Ancient Mountain Sentinel."
  - Southern Appalachia Forest Commission, 1992-2008, and undated (Box-folder 2:11)
    ‐ information about; fact sheet; bulletins; meeting agenda; Quarterly newsletters; "The Case for the Conservation of Aquatic Resources"; "Economic Contributions and Expenditures in the National Forests" report; conference agenda; correspondence; publications.
  - Southern Environmental Law Center, 1997-2009, and undated (Box-folder 2:12)
    ‐ memoranda, correspondence, contact list, agenda, executive summary, maps, brochures.
  - The Nature Conservancy, 1973-2006, and undated [Bulk 1973-1976] (Box-folder 2:13)
    ‐ correspondence, newsletters.
  - The Wilderness Land Trust, 2004 and undated (Box-folder 2:14)
    ‐ letter, email, donation card, thank-you card.
  - The Wilderness Society, 1968-1970, 2000, 2006 (Box-folder 2:15)
    ‐ correspondence; conference notes; newsletters.
  - Virginia Blue Ridge Railway Trail Foundation, 2000, and undated (Box-folder 2:16)
    ‐ railroad and project history; executive summary; maps.
  - Virginia Conservation Network, 1999-2006, and undated (Box-folder 2:17)
    ‐ correspondence and newsletters; bylaws.
  - Virginia Council of Trout Unlimited, 1992-2002 (Box-folder 2:18)
    ‐ reports; pro-wilderness declaration; handwritten notes; plan of action outline; activities.
  - Virginia Department of Game and Inland Fisheries, 2008, and undated (Box-folder 2:19)
    ‐ meeting notes.
  - Virginia Society of Ornithology, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 2:20)
    ‐ Officers and Committee chairmen lists; board of directors meeting notes.
  - Wild Virginia, 2004, 2008 (Box-folder 2:21)
- General Area Planning and Management Documents
  - Virginia Wilderness Resource Management Conference, 1978, 1984, 1986 (Box-folder 2:22)
    ‐ publication by U.S. Dept of Agriculture; UVA Alumni News, 1984; conference agenda and registration; correspondence; maps of conference area; brochures; handwritten notes; signup sheet for continued involvement in Mountain Lake.
  - Forest Service Master Plan, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 2:23)
    ‐ planning reports/procedures; publications by Dept. of Agriculture, Forest Service; correspondence; newspaper clippings; Master Plan Rough Draft; final copy; geological survey.
  - Forest Service Planning, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 2:24)
    ‐ brochures; periodical articles; correspondence; maps and tables; conference notes and agenda.
  - RARE II, Roadless Areas Review and Evaluation, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2:25)
    ‐ publications/maps; correspondence; user’s manual/instructions for rating; newsletters.
  - RARE III, Roadless Area Reviews (GWNF), 1983-1991 (Box-folder 2:26)
    ‐ correspondence; special interest areas; draft of papers for specific areas.
  - Forest Service Asset Management, 1982-1992 (Box-folder 2:27)
    ‐ decision memos: amendments (Wilderness Management); letter withdrawing decisions for amendments; U.S. Dept of Interior Fact Sheet; correspondence; newspaper clippings.
  - Extension and Management of Blue Ridge Parkway, 1970 (Box-folder 2:28)
    ‐ correspondence; Management Objectives; Data Summary (blue folder).
  - Bear Management Plan, 2001 (Box-folder 2:29)
    ‐ newspaper clippings; correspondence.
  - Management Prescription Draft for Southern Appalachia Forests (Box-folder 2:30)
    ‐ only contains a copy of the draft.
  - Wilderness Resources Council, 1979-1989 (Box-folder 2:31)
    ‐ newsletters, purpose and goals; buffer zones in VA.
  - District Plans – George Washington and Thomas Jefferson, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2:32)
    ‐ contains five proposals and accomplishments: Glenwood Ranger District, New Castle Ranger District, Blacksburg-Wythe Ranger District, Mt Rogers National Recreation Area, Clinch Ranger District.
  - 1997 Wilderness Areas, GW and TJ, 1997 (Box-folder 2:33)
    ‐ lists and candidates for wilderness designation; correspondence.
  - Ecological Classification System, 1996 (Box-folder 2:34)
    ‐ working draft by Margaret Trani Griep.
  - Guidelines – Wilderness Evaluation, 1997 (Box-folder 2:35)
    ‐ Final Draft Proposed Guides for Clarification of: Land and Resource Management Planning Handbook, Wilderness Evaluation, Roadless Area Evaluation.
  - Taxation by Land Use (Box-folder 2:36)
    ‐ copy of: Model Ordinance for Special Assessments for Agricultural, Horticultural, Forest or Open Space Real Estate.
- George Washington National Forest
  - Management Plan Revisions/Working Group, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 2:37)
  - GWNF Plan Recommendations/Revisions, 2007-2009 (Box-folder 2:38)
  - Waynesboro Group, 2007-2009, and undated (Box-folder 2:39)
  - Miscellaneous items, 1969-1993, and undated (Box-folder 2:40)
  - Bath County Power line Meetings, 1976 (Box-folder 2:41)
  - Benson Run and Sugar Tree, 2001-2003, and undated (Box-folder 2:42)
  - Big Levels, 1973-1991, and undated [Bulk 1973-1974] (Box-folder 2:43)
  - Signal Corps Knob Project- Deerfield, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 2:44)
  - Dolly Ann and Alleghany Highlands, 1979, 1998, 2005, and undated (Box-folder 2:45)
  - Dry River Ranger District General Items, 1982-1994, and undated (Box-folder 2:46)
  - Laurel Fork, 1972-2005, and undated [Bulk 1972-1973, 1994] (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Little River, 1991-2009 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Lower Jackson River Unit, 1974 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Massanutten, 1972-1976, and undated (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Mount Pleasant, 1986-1997, and undated (Box-folder 3:5)
  - North River, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Paddy Run, 2004 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Piney River, 1974-1975, and undated (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Ramsey's Draft, 1972-1991, and undated (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Rich Hole, 1976-1977, and undated (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Rough Mountain, 1979, 1983, 1987 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Skidmore Fork, 1990-1997, and undated (Box-folder 3:12)
  - St. Mary's River, 1997-2004, and undated (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Proposed Research of Green Pond and Skidmore Fork (Box-folder 3:14)
- Thomas Jefferson National Forest
  - Conference Call Notes, 1999-2009 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - 2002 Map Originals, 2002 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Citizen Task Force, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Jefferson Forest Planning (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Plan Revision Issues, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 3:19)